{
  "reference_number": "8451",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The ETS and carbon unit system seems to me to have been dreamed up by some financial wizard in order to make money. This\n should not be the foundation of a country making an honest attempt to address its emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Why would it be tied to a change of Government? It shouldn't be political but should be based on facts, how we are progressing, what\n\n is needed to reach the third budget and the effect on the country of doing so. These things should drive any amendments to the\n budgets, not an incoming government. Therefore review periods should be set."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Depends how flexible it is. We don't want to be locked into a suicide mission."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The practicalities, cost and impact on those affected, of actioning any plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The ETS is flawed and has resulted in the opposite of what was intended. It was set up for financial gain and this should not be the\nmotivation for addressing greenhouse gases. There should be honest accounting with every person and industry dealing with their\nown effects. An ETS shouldn't be required to achieve this."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There also needs to be practical knowledge of the most affected industries. Not industry representation as such, but people around\n\nthe table who can relate discussions to the actual practicalities."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Adapting to climate change is a whole other kettle of fish."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Deal with it separately because it will be happening at a different pace than emissions, and no-one knows what that pace is going to\n\nbe."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Deal with it separately. TA's in the first instance need to be working consistently on the effects of climate change and the issues are\nsimilar around the country so government needs to show leadership."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "To me it seems that to date the accounting system, including the ETS, has been broken. Emissions in a biological cycle should not\n\nbe included. Forestry is not the fix all that government seems to think, it has many negative effects as well. If the accounting is done\nproperly I suspect that NZ's emissions in the world scheme of things are miniscule. There is alot of other pollution here that should\n\nbe dealt to, look at all the garbage that stores like The Warehouse, and the other \"cheap crap\" stores which are popping up\neverywhere are bringing into the country all of which will ultimately end up in the landfill. Why don't you do something about that? And\n\nreducing packaging - the gains that we make by bringing our re-usable bags to the supermarket are all lost by the likes of Pams\nputting half a dozen tomatoes in a plastic container. And when you buy something the size of a matchbox on line, and it comes in a\nwhole lot of packaging? Why don't you do something about that? I think we will be buried in our own rubbish long before we run out of\n\noxygen or get frazzled by the sun."
    }
  ]
}
